Hyoungjoo Kim

hyoungjoo@cmu.edu

https://hyoungjook.github.io



in



RESEARCH INTERESTS

I'm interested in designing **Data-Intensive Software Systems** for **Next-Generation Hardwares**. My current research is designing **Databases** for **Processing-in-Memory** by pushing code towards data, and I'm also interested in **Disaggregated Memory** and **Distributed Systems**. Previously, I have worked on Machine Learning Systems and GPU clusters.

EDUCATION

• Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania

2023 - Present

Ph.D. Student in Computer Science Advisor: Phillip B. Gibbons

• Seoul National University, Seoul, Korea

2017 - 2023

B.S. in Electrical and Computer Engineering Advisor: Jangwoo Kim

GPA: 4.28/4.3 (2nd/148)
The period includes two years of mandatory military service in South Korea.

PUBLICATIONS

- Taebum Kim, **Hyoungjoo Kim**, Gyeong-In Yu, Byung-Gon Chun BPipe: Memory-Balanced Pipeline Parallelism for Training Large Language Models International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2023 (Oral Presentation)
- Hyoungjoo Kim

Modeling the GPU Instruction Scheduling Performance using Microbenchmarks Bachelor's Thesis, Seoul National University, 2023 (Advised by Jangwoo Kim)

RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCES

 Parallel Data Lab, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania Graduate Research Assistant 2023 - Present

- PIM-Friendly Database: (In Progress) Designing fast and efficient DBMS for Processing-in-Memory Systems
- Microsoft, Redmond, Washington Research Intern

Summer 2024

- : (Working towards publication)
- \bullet ${\bf FriendliAI},$ Seoul, Korea

2022 - 2023

Research Intern

- BPipe: Accelerating the training of LLMs by rebalancing memory utilizations
- GPU Kernel Optimization: Optimized CUDA kernels for training LLMs
- High Performance Computer System Lab, Seoul, Korea

2021

Undergraduate Thesis Project Student

- GPUDiag: Modeling GPGPU microarchitecture using automated microbenchmarks

- $\mathit{Multi-GPU\ gem5}\colon$ Extend gem5-APU to support multiple GPUs

• Geolux, Seoul, Korea Software Engineering Intern	2017 - 2018
- Pothole Detector: Trained AI models to detect potholes from driveway videos HONORS AND AWARDS	
• The Presidential Science Scholarship, Korea Student Aid Foundation	2017 - 2023
• Gold Medal, International Physics Olympiad (IPhO)	2016
• Silver Prize, Samsung Humantech Paper Award (for high school students)	2016
Intra- and Extracurricular Projects	
• Query Execution Engine for OLAP Database Systems	Spring 2024
• Cache Simulator for x64 binaries using pintool	Fall 2023
\bullet Linux Kernel $\mathit{Hacking}$ to impelement custom scheduler, lock, and file system	Spring 2022
• Compiler Frontend for custom grammar rules using lex and yacc	Fall 2021
\bullet CNN $\mathit{Accelerator}$ that can process conv, fc, and maxpool using Verilog and FPGA	Fall 2021
ullet CPU Simulator for pipelined CPU with branch predictor and cache using Verilog	Spring 2019
ullet IoT System on the car fender that alarms the driver of safety incidents	2019
ullet IoT System in the billiards ball that evaluates the cueing accuracy	2018
• 3D Territory Game that adds 3D graphics to the given game logic	Spring 2018
• Robotic Car that follows the path and escape from the maze	Fall 2017
\bullet Robotic Arm that mimics human arm movement	2017
\bullet $Robotic\ Arm$ using thermally-driven super-coiled-nylon artificial muscles	2015 - 2016
TEACHING EXPERIENCES	
• Teaching Assistant - "Operating Systems", Seoul National University	Spring 2023
SKILLS	

- \bullet C, C++, Python, CUDA, Verilog, Java, Linux Kernel, PyTorch, ZSim
- Computer Architecture and Simulation, GPUs, Machine Learning Systems, Operating Systems, Processing-in-Memory, Relational and Vector Databases